James Ryan Morris papers, 1959-1978
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
James Ryan Morris papers, 1959-1978
MS 268
Morris, James Ryan, 1935- 1978
The collection consists primarily of letters to James Ryan Morris from poets Diane Di Prima, Theodore Enslin, Jack Hirschman, William J. Margolis, Dan Propper, and Stuart Zane Perkoff.
.4 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
James Ryan Morris, born in New York City in 1935, served as a marine in Korea. He co-founded and co-edited the literay magazine Sight until its cessation in 1958, founded The Croupier (Seattle, 1965-?) and Mile High Underground (Denver, 1966-1967). Published collections of Morris' own poetry include She Said, The Rat's Nest, Diana's Smile, He Has Heard, 13 Sounds, .22 For Her, and The Hands. He has also published poetry postcards and broadsides.Morris died in 1978.
Organization
This collection is organized into five series.
Series I: Correspondence, 1959-1978
Series II: Broadsides, 1969-1971
Series III: Poetry and Published Works, 1961-1977
Series IV: Photographs, No Date
Series V: Miscellaneous Poetry and Graphics, 1967-1971
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists primarily of letters to James Ryan Morris from poets Diane Di Prima, Theodore Enslin, Jack Hirschman, William J. Margolis, Dan Propper, and Stuart Zane Perkoff. Letters from Perkoff to Anthony Scibella and Maxine Cherry are included, as well as typescripts and holographs of Perkoff's poetry. The collection also includes other correspondence, poetry books, poems, broadsides, two unidentified photographs, and graphics.
Morris, James Ryan, 1935-1978; Bly, Robert; Di Prima, Diane; Enslin, Theodore; Hall, Donald, 1928-; Hirschman, Jack, 1933-; Lifshin, Lyn; Margolis, William J; Perkoff, Stuart Z; Propper, Dan, 1937-; Tipton, James, 1942-; Poets, American -- 20th century -- Correspondence; Bohemianism in literature; Beat generation; Poems; Correspondence; Broadsides; Photographs
Separated Material
Publications received with the collection were removed and catalogued separately.
Container List
- Series I: Correspondence, 1959-1978
  - Stuart Z. Perkoff to Maxine Cherry and unknown parties. 1959-1962 (one undated) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Letter to Cherry from 801 Market Street, San Diego, California to 302 Market Street, Venice, California. Seven items.
  - Diane DiPrima to James Ryan Morris. 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Letters and postcards from San Francisco to Denver. Twelve items, some lacking dates.
  - Theodore Enslin to James Ryan Morris. 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Nine letters from Box 522 Temple, Maine to Golden, Colorado
  - Theodore Enslin to James Ryan Morris. 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Nine letters from Box 273 Mesquite, New Mexico to Golden, Colorado.
  - Jack Hirschman to James Ryan Morris. June 23, 1972-March 9, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    From Nevada City, California to Golden, Colorado. Nine items.
  - William Margolis to James Ryan Morris. March 5, 1961 to April 12, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    One letter and one postcard from Ward E-1, Veterans Administration Hospital, Long Beach, California to 65 Seaman Avenue, New York, New York
  - William Margolis to James Ryan Morris. October 12, 1962 to October 11, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Six letters from Guadalajara, Jalisco, Mexico to Seattle, Washington.
  - William Margolis to James Ryan Morris. March 3, 1965-August 1, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Six postcards and letters from 242 7th Street, Seal Beach, California to Seattle, Washington.
  - William Margolis to James Ryan Morris. November 25, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    One letter from 1827 E. 5th Street, Long Beach, California to Seattle, Washington.
  - William Margolis to James Ryan Morris. February 20, 1969-December 29, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Six letters and postcards from 4618 Prospect Avenue, Los Angeles, California to Denver and Golden, Colorado.
  - William Margolis to James Ryan Morris. January 25, 1971-October 24, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Twenty letters from 4618 Prospect Avenue, Los Angeles, California to Denver and Golden, Colorado.
  - Stuart Z. Perkoff to James Ryan Morris. June 30, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    One letter from an unidentified jail to Seattle, Washington.
  - Stuart Z. Perkoff to James Ryan Morris. April 24, 1965-November 12, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Three letters and postcards from Venice, California to Seattle, Washington.
  - Stuart Z. Perkoff to James Ryan Morris. July 17, 1969-January 27, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Twelve letters from Terminal Island Federal Prison, San Pedro, California to Denver, Colorado.
  - Stuart Z. Perkoff to James Ryan Morris. October 3, 1970-October 20, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Nine letters and postcards from Mill Valley, Californai to Denver, Colorado.
  - Stuart Z. Perkoff to James Ryan Morris. January 28, 1972-May 17, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Eleven letters and postcards from Larkspur and Mill Valley, California to Denver, Colorado.
  - Stuart Z. Perkoff to James Ryan Morris. June 8, 1973-December 18, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Four letters and postcards from Venice, California to Denver, Colorado.
  - Dan Propper to James Ryan Morris. January 6, 1973-March 7, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Nine letters from 143 Willow Avenue, Fairfax, California to Denver, Colorado.
  - Dan Propper to James Ryan Morris. July 3, 1975-June 6, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Twelve letters from Star Route 55C, Ramona, California to Denver Colorado.
  - Dan Propper to James Ryan Morris. April 20, 1978-May 31, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Three letters from Box 76 Ramona, California to Denver, Colorado.
  - Miscellaneous letters to James Ryan Morris. 1964-1978 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Twenty-two letters and postcards from various poets and others (several undated).
  - Allen Ginsberg to James Ryan Morris (postcard). January 10, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Stuart Z. Perkoff to Anthony Scibella, editor. ca. 1960 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    One letter referring to Morris in Seattle
  - Stuart Z. Perkoff to Anthony Scibella, editor. August 25, 1971-March 17, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Six letters and postcards from Mill Valley and Larkspur, California to Denver, Colorado.
  - Stuart Z. Perkoff to Anthony Scibella, editor. January 11, 1972-March 19, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Seven letters from Venice, California to Denver, Colorado.
  - Robert Bly to James Tipton. January 1, 1969-January 2, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Seventeen letters from Madison, Minnesota to Elwell and Kalamazoo, Michigan.
  - Donald Hall to James Tipton. September 24m 1970-April 10, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Seven letters from 1715 S. University Avenue, Ann Arbor, Michigan to Elwell, Michigan.
  - Lyn Lifshin to James Tipton. June 2, 1969-July 29, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Five letters, postcards, and a promotional flyer from 92 Rapple Drive, Albany, New York, to Elwell, Michigan.
  - Gary Snyder to James Tipton. August 16, 1976-April 2, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    One letter and one postcard from Alleghany Star, Route 963, Nevada City, California to Elwell, Michigan.
  - Miscellaneous letters to James Tipton. February 16, 1971-November 12, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Four letters and postcards, one undated, from William Heyen, Alvin Greenbert and Alfred (no last name).
- Series II: Broadsides, 1969-1971
  - Diane DiPrima. Broadsides and poetry postcards. Four items. 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Series III: Poetry and Published Works, 1961-1977
  - Lyn Lifshin: Poetry and reviews. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Black Apples
    Two typescript copes of James Tipton's review of the collection.
  - William Margolis: Poetry. 1961-1974 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Three poems in typescript dedicated to Stuart Z. Perkoff.
  - James Ryan Morris: Poetry. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    13 Sounds
    Diana's Smile
    He Has Heard
    I Invoke Mayakovsky (leaflet, two copies)
    For Pagan (broadside)
    A Poem for Legs (postcard)
    The Rat's Nest
    She Said
  - Stuart Z. Perkoff: Poetry and fiction. 1963-1967 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Some poems in typescript, other copied by unidentified persons after being smuggled from prison; published prose, "Isn't There Another Saxophone Player?" published in the May 1982 issue of Passion Press.
  - Stuart Z. Perkoff: Miscellaneous personal documents (correspondence relating to imprisonment and eulogy). 1969-1974 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Series IV: Photographs, No Date
  - Three miscellaneous portraits (Robert Bly?). no dates (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Series V: Miscellaneous Poetry and Graphics, 1967-1971
  - Miscellaneous items. 1967-1971 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Postcard
    Handbill
    Altered 1913 booking record for prisoner in Oakland, California
    Promotional flyer for Robert Bly